Faye Calvert Abrell papers, 1922-1999, C592
Indiana University Archives
Faye Calvert Abrell papers
1922-1999
1946-1947
Indiana University Archives
Abrell, Faye Calvert, 1909-2003
C592
1.6 cubic feet 3 boxes
Faye Calvert Abrell attended Indiana University and graduated with both a BS in Education in 1936 and a MS in Education in 1941. Following her time at Indiana University, Abrell spent 1946-1947 teaching in the Dependents School Service in war-torn Frankfurt, Germany and was involved in the Allied Forces mission of effecting a permanent peace. The majority of the collection reflects Abrell's year spent teaching abroad and includes correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks she made and souvenirs she collected while in Germany.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Biographical Note
Faye Calvert Abrell was born on February 20, 1909 in Freedom, Owen County, Indiana to Foster and Amy V. Abrell. Faye attended Indiana University and graduated with a BS in Education in 1936 and a MS in Education in 1941. Following her time at IU, Abrell sought employment with the U.S. Army as a War Department civilian employee in the U.S. Forces European Theater. As a result, she spent 1946-1947 teaching in the Dependents School Service, established in 1946, in war-torn Frankfurt, Germany, and was involved in the Allied Forces mission of effecting a permanent peace.
At the Dependents School, Abrell spent the year in the American occupied zone of Germany teaching American children who had moved overseas with their military families. During her periods of leave from teaching, Abrell travelled around Europe and during this time, visited Adolf Hitler's home (also known as "The Eagle's Nest) and attended some of the Nuremburg Trials.
The photographs taken by Abrell document the resiliency of the German people to continue forward and rebuild after World War II. Abrell photographed numerous views of the bombed buildings and countryside she witnessed during her year abroad. Abrell described the apartment building she lived in during her time in Frankfurt as "half bombed away," and the city of Frankfurt itself over 65% destroyed. In one of the journals within this collection, Abrell comments that she later returned in 1967 just to see the city of Frankfurt rebuilt.
Abrell was an elementary school teacher for Monroe County Schools until her retirement in 1975. She was actively involved in the community and in many organizations. Abrell died on March 8, 2003 at age 94.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: Biographical, Correspondence, Photographs, and Souvenirs.
Scope and Content Note
The Abrell papers are organized into four series: Biographical, Correspondence, Photographs, and Souvenirs.
The Biographical series ( 1922-1999 ) contains documents related to Abrell's work as a War Department civilian employee, journals she kept while in Germany, a biography of one of her friends, and certificates related to Abrell's academic and community involvement accomplishments. The files are arranged alphabetically by folder titles.
The Correspondence series ( 1944-1953 ) contains letters, postcards, cards, and telegrams that were exchanged during Abrell's year spent in Frankfurt, Germany. The bulk of the letters are between Abrell and her mother. The files are arranged by letters sent to Faye C. Abrell and letters from Faye C. Abrell to friends and family. The letters are further arranged within folders chronologically.
The Photographs series ( 1946-1947 ) contains photographs taken by Abrell during 1946-1947 and begin with photographs taken on the boat trip to Europe and ending with photographs from the boat trip back to America. Abrell also created several scrapbooks of her photographs, tickets, and souvenirs collected while teaching and travelling in Europe. Within the largest scrapbook Abrell kept, she pressed a flower she claims she took from a bouquet on Hitler's table and a piece of broken marble from his mantelpiece. Nearly every photograph has been labeled with details of the location, date, and names of individuals as described by Abrell. The photographs are arranged alphabetically by locations as labeled by Abrell.
The Souvenirs series ( 1944-1990 ) contains blank postcards, pamphlets from the Nuremburg Trials, a German-English/English-German Dictionary, restaurant menus, play billets, maps of Germany, and other miscellaneous pamphlets and articles collected during Abrell's year in Frankfurt, Germany. The files are arranged alphabetically by locations as labeled by Abrell.
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database
Acquisition Information
Accension 2008/084
Provenance
Transferred in October 2008.
Teachers--Germany--Frankfurt am Main--History--20th--century--Sources.; Germany--Description and travel.; Germany--History--1945-1955--Sources.; Abrell, Faye Calvert, 1909-2003 -- Archives; Abrell, Faye Calvert, 1909-2003 -- Correspondence; Abrell, Faye Calvert, 1909-2003 -- Travel
- Biographical, 1922-1999 (Box 1)
  - Awards and degrees, July 1922-March 1999 (Box 1)
  - "Biography of Eva Young Wiles", March 25, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1990-1994 (Box 1)
  - Delta Kappa Gamma Bulletin, "From Another Member in Frankfurt," Faye Abrell, Summer 1947 (Box 1)
  - Journals (Box 1)
    - "Memories of 1946-47 in Germany and ideas for speeches when I returned", 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - "Things I must remember and a list of pictures taken", 1946-1947 (Box 1)
    - Germany Trip, September 1946-August 1947 (Box 1)
  - Work Documents, March 1946-June 1947 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1944-1953 (Box 1)
  - Incoming (Box 1)
    - Amy Abrell (her mother), September 1946-August 1947 (Box 1)
    - Faye Calvert Abrell, September 1946-August 1947 (Box 1)
    - Friends, July 1946-December1946 (Box 1)
    - Friends, January 1947-July 1947 (Box 1)
    - Friends (after Germany), 1946-March 1957 (Box 1)
    - H.E. Binford, Superintendent School City of Bloomington, IN, March 1947-July 1947 (Box 1)
    - Glen & Bernice (after Germany), June 1949-July 1949 (Box 1)
    - Hannah, Office of Chief of Counsel for War Crimes, November 25, 1946-December 9, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Helen Hummel, November 1946-July 1947 (Box 1)
    - Dick & Virginia Meyering (after Germany), December 1947- February 1953 (Box 1)
    - Elizabeth Moore, December 1946-June 1947 (Box 1)
    - Ed Richardson, September 16, 1944-April 11, 1945 (Box 1)
    - Donald A. Rogers, Attorney-at-Law, Bloomington, IN, September 28, 1946-November 7, 1946 (Box 1)
    - Cathy (after Germany), January 3, 1950-February 23, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Mary Bell (after Germany), December 1950-June 1953 (Box 1)
  - Outgoing (Box 2)
    - Amy Abrell (her Mother) (Box 2)
      - August 1946-December 1946 (Box 2)
      - January 1947-August 1947 (Box 2)
- Photographs and scrapbooks, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Austria-Vienna, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Bombed downtown Frankfurt, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Bombed Old City, Baptist Church, Goethe house ruins, Shiller Statue (Frankfurt), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Brussels, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Casino: Party for Major Bell, April 1947 (Box 3)
  - Dachau Concentration Camp, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Denmark, Sweden, Norway, 1947 (Box 3)
  - France, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Frankfurt-Hammon St. (our apt.), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Frankfurt-McNarney Clay Ceremony, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Frankfurt-Palm Gardens German Schools, April 1947 (Box 3)
  - Frankfurt School Trips, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Frankfurt Zoo, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Bad Homburg, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Bad Nauheim (from/close to Frankfurt), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Berchtesgaden, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Berlin, Summer 1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Garmish Meeting, April 1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Heidlburg, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Munich, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Visit to Stutigart to see Gertrude Strickmayer, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Germany-Wiesbaden, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Hitler's Yacht, Hitler's home, etc., 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Italy and Rome, 1946 (Box 3)
  - London, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Luxembourg, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Mad King's Castle (near Oberammergau), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Marbourg, France to Switzerland, January 1947-July 1947 (Box 3)
  - Military Compound Frankfurt, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - "My class 3rd-4th (2 weeks), soon only 4th, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Northern Germany, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Nuremburg, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Obermmergau-Passion Play, Mad King's Castle, 1947 (Box 3)
  - On board the George Washington, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Prague, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Rhine River (blown up bridge), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Rome, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Saalburg-Fort dates to 100 AD, school trip, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Salzburg to Germany, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 3)
    - 1947 and following years after Germany (Box 3)
    - Austria, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Bad Homburg, Frankfurt, Amy Rutz (Mary in Passion Play), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Dachau and Frankfurt, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Frankfurt, Germany, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Frankfurt, Germany, My Class, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Frankfurt, Germany-Pictures I took, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Frankfurt Ruins "Pictures I took, (65% of Frankfurt destroyed), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Leaving Germany, August 1947 (Box 3)
    - London, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Italy, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Paris, France (Notre Dame), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Souvenirs, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - School Trips, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Vance: Ship home, 1947 (Box 3)
- Souvenirs, 1944-1990 (Box 3)
  - General, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Autographs on deck of cards from on board the George Washington, September 26, 1946-October 6, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, July 1946-February 1981 (Box 3)
  - Clippings and Souvenirs, 1944-1990 (Box 3)
  - German-English English-German Dictionary, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Goethe Museum, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Holland, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Ireland, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Maps of Germany and Frankfurt, June 1959 (Box 3)
  - "Mission Accomplished: Third United States Army Occupation of Germany, May 9, 1945-February 15, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Nuremburg Trials (Trial pamphlet and photos), 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, August 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Postcards of Bavarian Zugspitz Cable Car, mountains, etc., 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Postcards of Frankfurt, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Scotland, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Tickets and Leaves, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - "To be framed", 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - The U.S.A.T. George Washington autographs & photograph, to Frankfurt, Germany, 1946-1947 (Box 3)